<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An appeal to the churches of Christ for their righteous judgement in the matters of Christ, the concernments of all His glory, over whom there is a defence. Whether the way of Christ with His people be not paved-forth as a cause-way before them in His scriptures, and to be traced by the footsteps of all His neare-ones. Here you have the epistles only. The first to the churches, giving them some short account of their matters. The second unto the minister who enjoyned that work. The second unto the minister who enjoyned that work. The third to some neighbour-ministers for their judgement therein. The fourth to the Christian reader.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E868_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207694</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866731</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E868[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An appeal to the churches of Christ for their righteous judgement in the matters of Christ, the concernments of all His glory, over whom there is a defence. Whether the way of Christ with His people be not paved-forth as a cause-way before them in His scriptures, and to be traced by the footsteps of all His neare-ones. Here you have the epistles only. The first to the churches, giving them some short account of their matters. The second unto the minister who enjoyned that work. The second unto the minister who enjoyned that work. The third to some neighbour-ministers for their judgement therein. The fourth to the Christian reader.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed according to order for Henry Cripps in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on page [9]: Hezekiah Woodvvard.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Hezekiah Woodward".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Separatists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APPEAL To the Churches of Chriſt for their Righteous Judgement in the Matters of Chriſt, the concernments of <hi>All</hi> His Glory, over whom there is a Defence. <hi>Whether the way of Chriſt with His people be not paved-forth as a</hi> Cauſey-way <hi>before them in His Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to be Traced by the footſteps of all His neare ones.</hi> Here you have the Epiſtles only. The firſt to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, giving them ſome ſhort account of their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The ſecond unto the Miniſter who enjoyned that work. The third to ſome Neighbour-Miniſters for their judgement therein. The fourth to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>An high way ſhall be there, and a way, and ſhall be called the way of Holineſs. The uncleane ſhall not paſſe-over it. The way-faring men, though fooles, ſhall not erre therein.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 35. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>They have reproached the footſteps of thine Anointed, O Lord,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſ. 89. 51.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>The poore committeth himſelfe unto Thee,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 10. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Ipſa Dei Eccleſia quae in omnibus eſſe debet</l>
               <l>Placatrix Dei, quid eſt aliud quàm exacerbatrix?</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>The very Church of God [in account with men] that ſhould</hi> walke worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing, <hi>and ſo appeaſe His wrath, what elſe doe they, but by a contrary walking, imbitter His Holy Spirit, and provoke wrath.</hi> 
               <bibl>Salv: 3 Book page 87.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed according to Order for <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>WE are bold, upon the account of Truth, and right of humanity, to require this of him that reads this, That he would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a part, till he underſtand the whole [which ſhall be, if God permit, held-out before him in due time] If he will read any, let him read all, and forbeare cenſuring till he hath don reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſo well can we obſerve the perverſe act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men, that we have concluded, we ſhall never obtaine, what of right, we may require, and they of manners ſhould grant: for they feare, leſt overcome of us, of the Truth we meane, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lowd cry of it, like thunder in their eares, they ſhould be forced to give-up themſelves, as Conquered by it.</hi> Lact. 5<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Book firſt Chap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every man truely fearing God [Godly in Christ Jeſus] rejoyceth not in iniquity, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in the Truth; He is more than glad, He triumphs in this, That Truth hath Conquered him, and ſo is willing, yea and more than willing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycingly willing, to embrace it, and be led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by it.</hi> Naz.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:2"/>
            <head>To all thoſe, who looke for New Heavens, and a New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſſe, haſtening unto the Kingdome <hi>and patience of Jeſus Chriſt, when ſhall be a Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all His Holy Prophets ſince the world beganne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely Beloved in the Lord, Called and faithfull, Followers of God as deare Children; we, ſurely the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and moſt worth-leſſe among you all, have very lately, (ſuch <hi>lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring</hi> Spirits we have, O how loath to come out of our <hi>Sodom!)</hi> asked the <hi>way to Zion,</hi> with our <hi>faces thither-ward;</hi> and out of that broad way, we are <hi>pulled,</hi> the <hi>Lord being merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to us, in laying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ld upon our hand. And now we <hi>ſpeake often one to another</hi> (The Love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining) and to as many as will heare us, ſaying, <hi>Come, and let us joyne our ſelves unto the Lord</hi> in a <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Covenant,</hi> that ſhall <hi>not be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſee! and no more but what ye have ſeene, and doe ſee all the day long, how many Adverſaries from without, as many and more dangerous from within, ſtill ſtill oppoſing, contradicting, and blaſpheming, how many? yet Bleſſed be our God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we faint not; He, that at the firſt laid hold upon our hand, will hold us by the hand; It is enough; Wee ſhall never looke backe to <hi>Sodom</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:3"/> more, though our hearts, left to themſelves, are as bad as whoſe are worſt, and could eaſily <hi>forgett Lot's wife;</hi> and thoſe many, who <hi>have drawne back unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to detaine you long here. We may ſay as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, <hi>He did</hi> not <hi>finde</hi> the rude and raſcall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſo averſe from, contrary to, and ſet againſt the Lords worke, in his dayes, as he did, you know, whom. We leave others to their own experiences in theſe matters. This is ours; Wee finde none ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to us, as are the Miniſters of the Goſpel, all and every one of them, that are of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humphs:</hi> perſwaſion; (farre be it from us to meane or point to any other, whom we love, and honour heartily.) To open our matters morefully unto you, Thus it is; We are que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, yea charged by a godly Miniſter, as we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, who yet doth <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>Practiſe</hi> with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> That our way is not right, becauſe averſe from and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to (indeed it is, as the two remoteſt extreams are to) the ſaid Miniſters his way and perſwaſion, In point of Church. Adminiſtrations.</p>
            <p>Now we ſuppoſe, ye have read or heard, what that Gentlemans <hi>perſwaſion</hi> is, and how much he hath ſaid for it; how much alſo foure <hi>Worthies</hi> of the Lord, one after another, have ſaid againſt him, withſtanding him to his face. Indeed ſo much they have ſaid, and ſo clearely from the Scriptures, That to us, it ſeemes as much a wonder, That Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould, after all this, commend that way, bend to it, walke-on in it, ſpeak for it, draw Diſciples after them (with ſo much eaſe and delight, to walke together with them, that is no wonder) as it was to heare a Pope commended, the very <hi>plague</hi> alwayes of the Chriſtian world; And <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> among that curſed
<pb facs="tcp:119016:3"/> crue, extolled for a very <hi>holy Man,</hi> and a Panegyrick written of him; And yet, though he was, ſay their own men, the worſt of all men, ſo bad, that we ſhould bluſh to heare how bad he was, why yet, <hi>All the world wondered after the Beaſt?</hi> Whence we have concluded, That there is no perſon ſo vild, but his <hi>own</hi> have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and commended him. Nor any errour ſo groſs, nor opinion ſo deformed, nor example ſo <hi>pernicious,</hi> but as it is the more agreeing with the world, and to that principle within us, which <hi>drives</hi> us to incline towards it; ſo hath it alwayes found many Patrons ſtanding. up in their might for it, and many <hi>following</hi> after it. And therefore our wonder ceaſeth as to that matter. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Scripture muſt be full filled. A Carnall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery alwayes hath been, now is, and now is the time of their manifeſtation we hope, (which being well ſet is ſetling.) That they doe belong to that <hi>Out. Court,</hi> where the charge is, <hi>Leave it out, Meaſure it not.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. This their way, which is their folly, muſt needs be, as very taking with themſelves, ſo muſt it be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and maintained by them, being Calculated meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a Carnall intereſt. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. As taking with the people, as that can be, which is moſt pleaſing and taking; as ſweets with us which choak us; and graſſe with ſheep which rotrs them; for what more pleaſing than is this, To wallow in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mire of ſinne like a <hi>Swine;</hi> and yet to be well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed to the Lords Table as a <hi>Saint?</hi> No marvaile that many turne-in hether, and follow theſe <hi>pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes.</hi> So our wonder ceaſeth.</p>
            <p>We crave leave to proceed, That we may give you an account, why wee, the pooreſt of the flocke, have
<pb facs="tcp:119016:4"/> appeared againſt this way? Becauſe after all this, theſe, the Lords Worthyes have ſaid, We are queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned and charged, as aforeſaid, that we walke by a <hi>fancy,</hi> if we doe not walke that is ſenſe and practiſe with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humph<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> and thoſe Miniſters of his perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and practiſe, which is an abhorring to our Spirits. And now in point of Duty to our God, to our ſelves, to our Brethren, whom we love, as our ſelves, we could not be ſilent; <q rend="inline">For <note n="*" place="margin">Si accuſaius non reſpondeat, aut crimininis convictus, aut cerſe ſuſpectus videatur.</note> Silence, when we are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, either makes a full conviction, or ſtrengthens ſuſpicion.</q> Truely we ſaw it clearely our Duty, to vindicate that, which ſhould be more pretious to us, than the Gold of <hi>Ophir;</hi> The Glory of God; The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of His Houſe; our owne credit, in diſaſperſing our ſelves, and giving witneſſe to our wronged inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, as we could; our Brothers eternall good was alſo full in our eye; as it is in our heart, the weale, or proſperity of his everlaſting Soule.</p>
            <p>This farther account, we muſt give of our worke, the expoſing of it, to the view of the world; it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to a great volume, containing 60 ſheets, and more, which few or none of our Rank, whom yet we have a ſpeciall eye of Reſpect unto, have ſpare money to gett, or ſpare time to reade; ſo as we are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſend it forth by peece-meale, part after part, eight in all, which, we Conceive, may be made entyre, and compleate, containing diſtinct Subjects. And we begin, for the ſame reaſon, with the Epiſtles, which ſhew the occaſion, Contents, drift, ſcope, and end of the whole, and every part; That Epiſtle to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader we judge, of much concernment to him, and may ſuffice for his Information, in the higheſt matters, though he could reach to no more.</p>
            <p>Wee have yet farther Reaſon, which mooves
<pb facs="tcp:119016:4"/> ſtrongly with us to doe as aforeſaid in the ſending forth of our Matters peece after peece. (The maine and chiefeſt we omitt, being a point of Diſcretion we thinke ſo to doe; Only it may ſuffice to know <hi>ultra poſſe non eſt eſſe.</hi> What more is left to you to think) for</p>
            <p n="1">1. The matters we are upon, and manner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them will not down with the people (we ſpeak after our Country manner) no more than Gall and Worm wood will; yet we ſpeak not this in reference to our Country ſtile or Dialect, but in reference to the <hi>Truths</hi> here, which ye know are <hi>biting,</hi> ſtill, yea tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting <note place="margin">Viritates mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daces.</note> fleſh and blood. Indeed our matters are rough and harſh, not one <hi>ſmooth</hi> word, as fleſh will ſay, all along (yet, we hope, through Grace, that ſtrengthneth, we are not wholy unacquainted with <hi>Pauls</hi> holy <hi>craft,</hi> and bleſſed guile) for we <hi>feare God,</hi> and ſeek to <hi>pleaſe</hi> Him, and our Neighbour for his <hi>Good</hi> to <hi>Edification.</hi> Now they, that, with <hi>Ahab,</hi> count nothing <hi>good</hi> but what deſtroyeth them ſoule and body anon-after, though it ſeeme <hi>good</hi> now at preſent, God forbid we ſhould pleaſe ſuch, for they cannot be pleaſed but with <hi>Deceits, Propheſies of wine &amp; ſtrong Drinke.</hi> So now few will read us. The Gallioes of theſe times, looſe and prophane Libertines, theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard none of theſe things; Carnall Goſpellers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal profeſſors, thoſe regard as little: What or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Rebukes ungodlineſſe, or would advance the power of godlineſſe, is an abomination to them: Smooth upon ſmooth runs ſmoothly away; And that which is ſweet, goes down ſweetly. More of that which is ſweet (ſaid <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> hearers of old, as He tells us) though it choak us.</p>
            <p>Yet O that they could conſider the <hi>later end,</hi> what a <hi>ſower</hi> farewell <hi>ſweet</hi> will have. O that they could
<pb facs="tcp:119016:5"/> bethink themſelves what will become of them in that day, when the haile ſhall ſweep away the refuge of lies, and the <hi>waters ſhall overflow the</hi> Hiding place, and the <hi>well-built wall,</hi> in conceit, <hi>ſhall be rent with a ſtormy wind in His fury,</hi> when it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Where is the daubing wherewith ye have daubed it?</hi> Iſa. 28. 17. Ezek. 13. 11, 12. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good Miniſters, and a good people, not a few, as in charity we are ready to Judge, will ſtick at our matters; for our affections cannot eaſily fall-in there (the greater is our fault, if not our crime) where our judgement falls-out. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the laſt place; we are indeed the pooreſt of the flock, truely and indeed leſs than the leaſt. And ever the leſs any one is, the leſs regard will be had to what he ſaith (It would goe to the heart of them, if it were ſo with their God, but with Him the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs find mercy, a gracious wellcome, yea a glorious acceptance, but we were ſaying) The worth of the ſpeaker, addeth weight to his words; for as the man is, among men, ſuch is his ſtrength, and as his worth is, ſuch is the worth of his words. This onely we can ſay, and we truſt in ſingleneſſe of heart we doe ſay it, That (1) we love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity. And (2) That our intentions are ſingle, and cary level, in deſire and endeavour, to his Glory, and our Brothers everlaſting good. And then we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſo may you with us, as a worthy man conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for us all, <hi>The ſingleneſſe of the intention, is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacrificium, Medullatum.</hi> Mr. <hi>Jen.</hi> upon <hi>Jude</hi> 371.</note> 
               <hi>ſweet of a performance, and makes it even a Sacrifice with MARROW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we break-off, commending you to God, and the Word of His Grace, praying with all prayer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with you; That He, who is able to build-us-up,
<pb facs="tcp:119016:5"/> and to give us an inheritance among all them who are ſanctified, would make us perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle us; for ſo an entrance ſhall be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto us aboundantly, into the everlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Seen, alowed and ſubſcribed by their Paſtor,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>HEZEKIAH WOODVVARD.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:6"/>
            <head>A faithfull Account given-in by faithfull Brethren of the ſame minde, way and judgement, in the matters of Chriſt; To a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter of Chriſt (as it is meet for them <hi>to think) upon his earneſt requeſt, or rather Charge, That they would give him Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-grounds or reaſons of their judgement</hi> and practiſe, ſomewhat different, if not Contrary to his,</head>
            <list>
               <head>In Reference to theſe particulars.</head>
               <item>I. <hi>To Free admiſſion of all Infants to Baptiſme, and growne-perſons to the Lords Table.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>To the obſervation of that Day we commonly call Chriſtmas-Day.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>To Formes of prayer; ſpecially the Lords prayer; and foure Queries thereupon.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Relating</note>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>To a Nationall Church, whether ours is as the Jewes was?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>To the principles of Infant Baptiſme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. <hi>To the power, The Law of a Relation written upon the heart of Miniſters and people by the finger of God, hath to make them walke with a right-foote in the way of God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are digeſted into ſeaven Sections; the Contents whereof you have in the Epiſtle to the Rev: Miniſters.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Job 32. 17, 18.</bibl> 
               <hi>I will anſwer alſo my part, I alſo will ſhew my opinion; for I am full of matter, the Spirit within me conſtraineth mee.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 23. 28.</bibl> 
               <hi>He that hath a Dreame, let him tell a dreame? he that hath my word, let him ſpeake my word, faithfully: What is the Chaffe to the Wheat, ſaith the LORD?</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Titus 1. 9.</bibl> 
               <hi>Holding faſt the faithfull Word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine, both to Exhort, and to Convince, the gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 3. 15.</bibl> 
               <hi>Be ready allwayes to give an anſwer to every Man, that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſſe and feare.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:6"/>
            <head>A Letter annexed to theſe Papers, when by the Brethren, they were preſented to the Reverend Miniſter, requiring a <hi>Reaſon of their doings.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no little Difference betwixt us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Opinionum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietas &amp; opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium unitas, non ſunt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in opinion, none at all, we truſt in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; which ſhall appeare, we hope, on our part, in the manage of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between us all along. It were well if we could be every way accorded. And we think theſe words preſſe hard upon us, to</hi> ſtrive <hi>in this thing, that there be no ſtrife at all.</hi> There <hi>was a ſtrife between the heardmen of</hi> Abrahams <hi>Cattle, and the heard-men of</hi> Lotts <hi>Cattle, and the</hi> Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>and the</hi> Perrezite <hi>dwelled then in the Land,</hi> Gen. 13. 7. <hi>They did not walke in wiſdome towards them that were without. The enemies of God could diſcerne, being quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted that way, There were animoſities—that which ſhould not be among the Lords own people: Therefore faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Abraham, <hi>beſtirres himſelfe, for it was high time, and</hi> ſprang, <hi>or</hi> ranne-<hi>in</hi> (to <hi>uſe that word, and witneſſe the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>haſte he made)</hi> Let there <hi>be no ſtrife I pray thee between</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 14. 14. 16. 29.</note> 
               <hi>thee and me, and between my heardmen and thy heardmen, for wee be</hi> men-brethren, <hi>verſe 8: This is commended to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 7. 26.</note> 
               <hi>your ſerious thoughts, and the Lord grant it may abide upon ours. For Diviſions among brethren, makes friends mourne, and enemies within laugh and ſcorne, and hinders them that are</hi> without <hi>from making offer to come in. Let Gods</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:7"/> 
               <hi>people walk as becometh, ſtudy to be quiet, follow after peace, act nothing while they be angry, not giving place to it, no not for an houre, for that were to give place to the Devill. The Preacher tells us, that anger reſteth in the boſome of fooles; and paſſion dwells at the ſigne of folly; we are never angry, and ſinne not, but when we are angry at nothing but ſinne. Factions cauſe Fractions; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity makes ſtrong.</hi> David <hi>pray'd heartily, ſo ſhall we by his grace,</hi> Lead <hi>me in a plaine path becauſe of mine</hi> obſervers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 11 Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <hi>we reade, who are obſervers, they note diligently what we that are men-Brethren doe: The Lord humble us for the pride of our hearts (It is likely you may pray ſo too,) from whence comes warres and fightings among us? For untill we are well humbled, we ſhall doe nothing well, nor can we ſuffer, as Chriſtians for well-doing. The Lord humble us, ſuch need we have to pray this prayer againe, make us vile in our owne eyes, and then it will be no trouble at all how vile we are in others eyes. And all our things ſhall be done in Charity, (which ſhewes us what we are <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non facium bonas vel malos mores, niſi boni vel mali amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> Aug. Ep: ad Maced:</note>) wherein wee ſhould abound one towards another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We come to that now, we would ſay to you at the porch, or entrance to our worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We have anſwered your deſire in giving you here an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your matters; how ſhort of your expectation, or full-up unto it we know not. Only this we know, our ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and earneſt endeavours were to pleaſe God, and our</hi> Neighbour for his Good to Edification <hi>in all we have done, keeping cloſe to His rule laid before us in His Word. And having ſo done, we would hope, we have not diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you. This being the way, you and wee muſt take if we goe right; In the</hi> active <hi>obedience, what we doe, we labour to pleaſe God; In the</hi> paſſive, <hi>we endeavour, what He doth may pleaſe us. Exceeded we have all expectations, yours and our owne, in the largeneſſe of our Worke, whereunto we will ſay as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It falls out in matters of this Nature as in building, The coſt and paines amounts to double as much, as at firſt was intended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Your Brothers Book of</hi> Infant Baptiſme <hi>accidentally coming to our hands (for as we heard not of it, ſo we ſought not for it) put us to an after-trouble, altogether as great as the former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If it be ſaid, we are tedious herein, we can clearely ſay, it was to make Truth's cleare, we conſidered withall to whom we ſpeake, at leaſt, whom we would have to heare, poore ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ignorant Country folke, who are taken wholy with the rind or bark, the out-ſide of Sacrament, to whom if you ſpeake conciſely, little and ſhort, you ſpeake nothing at all; poſſibly a man may, though we cannot, ſpeake much in a little; but ſurely we commonly underſtand but little in much: Therefore it was not beſide our purpoſe to be ſo large, nor beyond the marke we ſended to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>You ſpeake highly of Mr.</hi> Hu<hi rend="sup">s</hi>: <hi>we ſuppoſe it was in favour to his way, and in love to us, that we might walke in his way. We would ſuppoſe alſo, thus highly you ſpake of him, hearing much good of him, from thoſe that may have little good in them, we meane, you might ſpeake by heare-ſay, not by what you had found in him, by reading his Books, you call them too,</hi> The works of the fleſh. <hi>So we would ſuppoſe, becauſe we would not queſtion the ſoundneſſe of your judgement, as to thoſe matters you may finde in the worke he hath made. But whatever you doe, or have done, we judge of a Man by his workes, as of a tree by his fruits. And this we muſt ſay of him, as once holy</hi> Fox <hi>of an unholy Biſhop,</hi> He was a Divine little ſeaſoned with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. And for his book, <hi>ſaid that Saint on earth, long ſince in Heaven, I would tell him to his Teeth, were we face to face,</hi> That it is a grievous plague to the Common ſafety of Chriſtians. <hi>Yet becauſe you might intend our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:8"/> 
               <hi>good in mentioning, that—Man and his workes unto us (and ſurely through grace, for we have it in us readily to comply with, and greedily to catch at ſuch works of the fleſh, but through grace, we have, as others may doe, gained much good by it, to advance our Love to Gods way, and our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to his) we will returne your Love as we can, onely in this, making honourable mention unto you, of three the Lords Worthies, (we need not mention Doctor</hi> Drake <hi>to you) that have made Anſwer to Mr</hi> Humphs: <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Palmer, <hi>Mr</hi> Hum: Saunders, <hi>(whoſe booke, hath wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Mr</hi> Tho: Mantons <hi>Epiſtle before it) Mr</hi> John Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins; <hi>we mention them in the ſame order, they came forth, and to our hands; and not before we were Come to the Cloſe of our worke. The laſt of theſe, Mr</hi> Jo: Collins <hi>hath given the people an Antidote againſt the poyſon of his laſt booke. We heartily Commend theſe to your reading; knowing no other meanes, whereby to commend our Love unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo,</hi> Sir, <hi>having more to ſay to your beloved Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and by us as much honoured; and then to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader, we will leave the matters here under Debate, to better judgement; And the Lord God of judgement be with them, that ſhall make judgement thereof, which by the ſupply of the Spirit is what it is, as wee by His grace are what we are. Only this we would Remember your ſelfe, your Brethren, and our ſelves off, That all thoſe matters we have, perhaps, too rigidly, or poſſible, too haſtily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately paſſed our judgement-upon, muſt have another day of hearing, and then be called over againe. Therefore we ſay againe. The Lord helpe us to give up our judgements unto the Lord, that ſo we may judge righteous judgement. And to begin at home with our ſelves, judging there every one of us, where God hath made us Judges: And enquire in the firſt place what truth is wrought in the inward parts,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:8"/> 
               <hi>which will quickly ſhew-forth it ſelfe in out-workes, ſo as others may ſee what is within, by what is done without, and glorifie our Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>So we heartily take our Leave of you for this time, and at this place; and Leave you and your Brethren to your owne time for peruſall of theſe matters, as they ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your hands, and then to deale therein, as they, after ſerious debate about them, ſhall require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Lord God proſper you, and bleſſe your Labours faithfully undertaken for Him, as ſure He will if you</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>earneſtly,</hi> to be accepted in Him, <hi>as the ambitious Man doth to clamber to the pinnacle of honour here below. And with you bleſſe all your faithfull Brethren all over the Nation, with one minde, heart, lippe, and ſhoulder, That by your and their meanes, the glorious Sun of the Goſpell may ſpread all over the ſame, as the morning ſpreads upon the mountaines, That His people all may walke by the light thereof, as Friends and</hi> Fellow-helpers <hi>to</hi> The Truth, <hi>preaching one thing, and praying as all may agree, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all the good people in all the Nations will ſay Amen; and wee with them, Amen and Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:9"/>
            <head>To the Reverend and Learned, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Bateman,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Will: Jemmatt,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chriſtop: Fowler,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Will: Brice,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tho: Owen,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>—<hi>Hartley.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare and honoured Sirs.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E the pooreſt of the flocke, and in the account of the World (which was, and now is, the Caſe of our betters) as the filth there and off-ſcouring of all things, have found our ſelves preſſed, after we had made our addreſſes to God, to appeale un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, who ſtand in His ſteede, and are Stewards in His houſe, hoping you can looke off from our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as meane and deſpicable as ye can thinke us, and looke on the matters here preſented before you, of neare alliance, we judge to your office, which is to take care, that all things be done in Gods houſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to decency, and right order, as well becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe, who have this ſtill in their thoughts, how they may magnifie their office, and give up their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with joy, when the time cometh they muſt be no longer Stewards. This is the ſcope we drive to, as He knowes, That knowes all things.</p>
            <p>The things inſiſted upon here, are digeſted into ſeaven Sections, foure referre to the clearing of theſe particulars.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:10"/>
            <p n="1">1. Whether all Infants borne of Baptized Parents, are to have admiſſion To Baptiſme?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether all perſons are to have the like free admiſſion to the Lords Table?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the obſervation of the Day we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> may paſſe with the allowance of any true Chriſtian?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether formes of prayer are good for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or of any uſe for the good to teach them to pray? And in reference to the Lords Prayer there are foure <hi>Queries.</hi> 1. Whether a wicked Man may ſay that prayer? 2. Whether a godly-man may take it into his Cloſet? 3. Or a godly Miniſter into his Pulpit? 4. Whether a godly Parent may teach it his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Together with theſe this is is queried and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whether <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray by giving them formes of Prayer to ſay?</p>
            <p>All theſe we have from Gods word, as we ſuppoſe, reſolved in the Negative, being preſſed to give our perſwaſion in reference to theſe matters.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And in the fift Section have endeavoured to make full proofe, That it is the Duty of every godly Miniſter reſolved in his Conſcience as to the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in all theſe, to hold it forth before his people in due time and place.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the ſixt, after we have given a fuller account of our matters, which, for haſte, was omitted in our Preface, we argue againſt a Nationall Church, that ours is not as the <hi>Jewes</hi> once was; and we give our reaſons wherefore we contend againſt it; As alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the principles of Infant Baptiſme as they are declared unto us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In the ſeaventh, and the Laſt, is ſhewen how prevailing The Law of a Relation written upon the
<pb facs="tcp:119016:10"/> heart by the finger of God, is with Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to point them to, and to hold their foote faſt in the way of holineſſe.</p>
            <p>We ſuppoſe now, ye would be cleared in this firſt, why we meddle in theſe matters? To this we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer you a very briefe account in this place, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpoken largely unto it in the ſecond part of our Preface, and firſt leaves in the firſt, and ſixt Sections.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have, through unſpeakable grace, our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the Father, and with His Son Jeſus Chriſt; And Goſpel Communion one with another: And, bending towards Church-order, as the Head and King thereof, hath taught us in His Goſpel, we are to hold it out from His Word, having a lowde Call ſo to doe, That <hi>our workes are wrought in God,</hi> in the power and ſtrength of God; at the Command and by the Authority of God; And that we are not afraid of the light, but readily offer our ſelves &amp; our workes unto it; to the <hi>ballance,</hi> or to the <hi>touchſtone,</hi> not doubting but they ſhalbe found weight &amp; right; And that our practiſe ſhall be found regular accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods Word in all things ſo farre as the Father of lights hath been pleaſed to Communicate of His light unto us, from which we would not decline wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly an hairs breadth for all the worlds good: for ſhould we doe ſo, we ſhould live, not, (which is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt us by one amongſt you) by <hi>faith</hi> in Church-order, but by <hi>fancy.</hi> The matters we have been queſtioned about, are here debated on in the foure firſt Sections; wherein we humbly give our opinion, and tell our perſwaſion as we ſtand fully ſatisfied in our own mindes, who <hi>muſt live by our own Faith,</hi> Rom. 14. 5. 23. We will onely repeate what hereafter wee have ſaid to this our undertaking;
<pb facs="tcp:119016:11"/> we have been, if we may ufe that Perſian word, <hi>anga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riati; Compelled</hi> to doe, as now we have done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place, it is likely ye would have our Reaſon, wherefore we appeale to you? It was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we were not willing to ſtand to the Umperage of one ſingle perſon among you, for though with us it is a very ſmal thing, that we ſhould be judged of him, or of mans judgement; Yet he being of the ſame judgement, in point of free admiſſion to the Lords Table (ſo he hath declared himſelfe) with Mr <hi>Hums:</hi> that unworthy man, whom the Lord God we feare in his righteous judgement hath <hi>given over to a minde voyde of judgement.</hi> Therefore we have made our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to you, beloved in Chriſt, who can ſo well remember, we muſt all appeare, before God, give to Him an account of our doings, to whoſe judgement, in His owne matters, we all appeale now, for to that we muſt ſtand anone after. We would adde to this ſome particulars more, for the further clearing our ſelves, and our undertakings unto you. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. We would ſpeake two things (which were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in our Preface to the firſt Section) (1) To that <hi>remote right</hi> an Infant hath to Baptiſme borne of wicked parents. The judgement, you know, of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines very Learned, &amp; godly, and poſſibly your own judgement alſo. To this we tell our perſwaſion, and our Faith, That a parent notorious for his Deboiſery may Cut-off himſelfe &amp; his poſterity from all Church priviledges, as well now as formerly it was: When <hi>Iſmael</hi> a member of the Church &amp; Circumciſed, grew to a prophane mocking of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he was caſt-out of the Church as unworthy to continue in that holy fellowſhip, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 9, 10, 11, 12. And <hi>Eſau</hi> his Fathers darling being very indulgent to him; yet for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:119016:11"/> deſpiſing his birth-right, the hand of God cut him off from the inheritance both of the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and of the bleſſing. Whence it was, That he was deprived of Church-fellowſhip, and his poſterity deprived both of Church-fellowſhip and of the ſeale of the Covenant. And ſo <hi>Jeremiah</hi> reckoneth-up <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> among the Nations uncircumciſed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 26. It is our perſwaſion as we finde it made out by others, That a Debauched parent may caſt himſelfe out of the Church now, and from all priviledges of the ſame, as ſoone and ſooner now under this Goſpel light, than they did under the Starre-light of the Law. And (2) Thoſe godly Miniſters, that doe admit all Infants to Baptiſme upon account of that <hi>remote</hi> right there-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when they ſpeake <hi>de jure</hi> what ought to be, (as he that hath ſpoken laſt, hath ſpoken much that way) they ſpeake, as he, very ſafely and holily, <hi>Children of Beleiving Parents ſhould be admitted to Baptiſme.</hi> But when they ſpeake <hi>de facto,</hi> what is done, and allowed off to be done, here they walk at large, and give more Liberty, than, we humbly conceive, the word of God, gives them. But howſoever, if they can ſatisfie their Conſciences in a larger latitude, they will not, we hope, judge others that cannot ſo doe; Conſcience being ſuch a tender thing, and cannot be <hi>forced</hi> no more than a <hi>parable</hi> ought to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have ſpoken ſomewhat Confidently againſt free admiſſion to the Lords Table, as they uſe to doe who are perſwaded, they have truth on their ſide; and the word of truth to warrant what they ſay. And indeed the more arrogantly Mr <hi>Hums:</hi> hath ſpoken to maintaine the Affirmative, the more confidently we have ſpoken in maintenance of the Negative: for why ſhould not we be as bold for our Lord Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:119016:12"/> as he is, beyond all expreſſion, ſhameleſsly bold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him. We are perſwaded in our ſoules, That the Lord of glory hath written in ſo faire and legible Characters, who are, and who are not to be admitted to His table, that He who runs may reade. We have heard of a Godly man, that ſaid to a wanton Lady (complaining of the darkneſſe and obſcurity of the Scriptures, though too well acquainted with the works of darkneſſe) what more plaine than this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid he? <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi> So indeed we may ſay, what more plaine that this, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>If thou</hi> take forth the <hi>pretious</hi> from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Mouth;</hi> Let them <hi>returne</hi> unto thee, but returne not thou unto them. What more plaine then this? They ſhall teach my people the difference between <note place="margin">Ezek. 44. 23.</note> the holy and prophane; and cauſe Men to diſcerne, between the uncleane, and the cleane.</q> And what more plaine then is the complaint of the Lord againſt thoſe Preiſts, who did not doe according to their Charge? <hi>Her</hi> Preiſts have violated my law; and have prophaned my holy things: how ſo? <hi>They have</hi> put <note place="margin">Ezek. 22. 26.</note> no difference between the holy and prophane, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have they ſhewed difference, between the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and the cleane. What more plaine then this? <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>If any Man</hi> that is called a Brother be a Fornicator, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 11. 2 Joh. 10.</note> or Covetous, or an Idolater, or a Railer, or a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch an one <hi>no not to eate.</hi>
               </q> Such groſſe ſinners are no more to be ſuffered in Holy Aſſemblyes, then ſwine in your garden, than toads in your diſhes, than dead flyes in a box of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (to uſe worthy Mr <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> his gloſſe upon that Scripture) What more plaine than this? <hi>Ye cannot be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 21.</note> 
               <hi>partakers of the Lords Table, and the Table of Devills.</hi> What more plaine then this? <hi>What fellowſhip hath righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:119016:12"/> with unrighteouſneſſe? What communion hath light with darkneſſe? What Concord hath Chriſt with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial? or what part hath he that beleiveth with an Inſidell? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idolls?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walke in them; and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; Whereſore Come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and be ye</hi> ſeperate <hi>ſaith the Lord God, and touch not the uncleane thing.</hi> What more plaine than all this; and this which followes. <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Revel. 21. 27. 22. 15.</note> 
               <hi>enter into it any thing that defileth. Without ſhall be dogges.</hi> Ye know what the Learned ſay of thoſe Scriptures. All agree, we thinke, That the houſe of God, the Church of the living God muſt be kept cleane by the Stewards there of. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leg. Aug Martor. in</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. 11. 1, 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have beleived; and thus confidently we have ſpoken in all things where we obſerved the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> with the <hi>Word</hi> going before us; and herein we appeale to you, as to the Truth of theſe matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the Negative we may erre, as weake ſimple men uſe to doe; but this we can ſay, we doe not <hi>erre in our hearts;</hi> if we erre, It is as a wearied traveller may doe, he erreth in his way, but ſore againſt his will, and thankes him heartily, that will tell him he is out of the way; and points him to it. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. We hope, we have not done that which we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to doe, made the leaſt reflection of Diſhonour upon you, or any of your brethren of the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an way. Some one of us have read their bookes, wherein they declare their Steward-like care to keep the Table of the Lord from prophane mixtures. And what they have ſpoken with the mouth, and declared with their pen <hi>de jure</hi> what ought to be, we would hope they performe with their hands, <hi>de facto,</hi> that is,
<pb facs="tcp:119016:13"/> they practiſe accordingly, as they ſtand cleared in their judgements they ought to doe. Yet</p>
            <p n="4">4. We cannot ſee, how the Godly Miniſters can anſwer their God, or their own Conſciences, when they can maintaine fellowſhip and keepe Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſuch as they judge not godly, being of their owne opinion and in their way; And not maintaine fellowſhip (it is cleare ſome of them doe not) with ſuch as in charity they judge godly, becauſe they are not of their opinion and in their way. <note place="margin">Idem eſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ad Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; ad rem. Ariſt. Qui amat ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prd, amat infrd upon, 1 Joh. 5. 1.</note> A godly man loveth all that are godly; and thoſe moſt, that moſt excell in godlineſſe, in them he delighteth, with them he converſeth, them he honoureth. <hi>Sicut ſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ſimplitèr ad ſimpliciter, it à magis ad magis,</hi> If Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be the reaſon why we love, then the more god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, the more love.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We can ſpeake this clearely, though we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from ſome in our opinions, yet not from any in our affections, how different ſoever unto us in their judgements. We love him, and them dearely, we oppoſe in theſe following matters heartily. We can ſay, and doe, as we ſay, love M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hum<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> though we doe not diſlike only, but loath his—Scrible as we ſhould doe ſin or hell it ſelfe. For ſurely the ſinne of Diviſion is the greater, when we make Religion to Patronize it. It is the manner not of a few to divide from one another, under a pretence, as if they made it Religion to bite and devoure one another. Surely <hi>this virgin is forced,</hi> for there is nothing more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Name or nature of Religion, than to cauſe or further-on diviſions. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dictam eſſe Religionem, quod quaſi in faſcem Domini vincti &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ſumus dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it.</hi> Hieron. By Religion we are made Gods bundle, firſt tied to Him, then one to another.</note> 
               <hi>Religio à religando,</hi> The name caries ſtrong union with it from binding us againe to God, and to one another, after we were divided from Him by our ſinne. We hope, we ſhall be found
<pb facs="tcp:119016:13"/> all along ſo farre from doing that, which <hi>Nazianzen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat.</hi> 12.</note> condemnes in pleading for the Truth, <hi>bely one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> we are <hi>faſtened</hi> to Chriſt, yet looſened <hi>our ſelves; we are for peace,</hi> yet we fight one with another; ſo far from this too ordinary among Chriſtians (as if that were the way to maintaine Truth) that we ſhall not let a rude word paſſe from us. Yet if any ſhould ſound that way, or be miſtaken rudely for <hi>Cuttingly,</hi> (we Engliſh it <hi>ſharply,)</hi> Let it be underſtood as it is meant and intended, ſpoken againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hum<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> onely, (againſt whom we could ſharpen our words, as <hi>Paul</hi> did his againſt <hi>Elimas,</hi> Acts 13. 9, 10.) and thoſe that are fully of his way and judgement, and this after they had read his (how loth we are to call Books, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, That great Philoſopher, and Learned Lo: <hi>Verul:</hi> denies that name to things of that <hi>make,</hi> having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, nor honeſty to patronize them, And ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring worſe in the Noſtrills of all the Godly, we thinke, than doe the worſt excrements of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon) whereby that rude man, juſtifies his way, and in ſo doing hath dealt rudely with our Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in heaven, blaſpheming His practiſe with His Saints, when he tabernacled on the earth.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If it be objected againſt us, That (1) we cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the writings of the Learned and godly; we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reply no; we cenſure them not, we bring the writings of men (in reference to ſet formes of prayer) to the Scriptures of God, the duty of every man, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in that ballance, and trying them by that touchſtone, whether they hold weight, and proove themſelves Gold. Thoſe more Generous <hi>Eereans</hi> might have truſted <hi>Paul</hi> as ſoone as any man alive, That he would not ſpeake a word, which wanted a graine of weight, yet their eares (a pair of ballances
<pb facs="tcp:119016:14"/> in the Hebrew) would weigh the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> though He had an infallible Spirit, and ſpake by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration immediately from heaven; <hi>Auditus &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectus,</hi> hearing and underſtanding ſhould goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and that each may doe its proper worke, our eare muſt try mans words, not taking them-up upon Truſt. Indeed what the Lord God ſpeaks <hi>once,</hi> we ſhould heare <hi>twice,</hi> without more to doe, onely to doe it in our lives, as thoſe uſe to doe, who have heard God ſpeake with the ſenſitive eare of their bodies, and the intellectuall eare of their ſoules; and ſo what He ſpake <hi>once,</hi> they heard <hi>twice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, if it be ſaid in the ſecond place, that we doe unbecoming our meane Condition, when we take upon us to adviſe and Councell our betters; Let it be obſerved, That our Counſell is pointed to them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before mentioned; and theſe have as much need of it, as any perſons ye or we know in all the world. Yet ye ſhall finde, we hope, this Counſell is given in much love. And if it be ſo taken, all will be well, though it be a Reproofe, which is good Counſell made keen and ſharpened; and not a hairs-bredth from our Rule; <hi>Them that ſinne,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5. 20. (ſcandalouſly and to the offence of others, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hump<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> hath done, and as doe all that are in his way) <hi>Rebuke</hi> before all, that others alſo may <hi>feare.</hi> We would adde hereunto, That we know no other way to manifeſt our Love <hi>openly,</hi> but by open Reproofe; <hi>Open Rebuke being better then ſecret Love,</hi> Pro. 27. 5. And to hate a brother, and not to rebuke him, are equivalent expreſſions in that Law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 17. we are aſſured we have not brought a railing accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt that Railing man; for ſo we ſhould not have done, had we contended with the Devill. But
<pb facs="tcp:119016:14"/> ſo he hath done with worthy D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Drake,</hi> taking his Lords part againſt that Scrible, wherein he blaſphemeth his Lord; and then what wonder if he raileth upon his ſervant.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We have but two words more, and then we have done. If ye finde Art wanting here all along (It were a wonder ye ſhould not, if you daine to looke through any part of it) it is a ſmall want; and not unbecoming us to ſpeak like our ſelves. We love the Cauſe dearely we here maintaine, relating as we judge, ſo nearely to our Lord Chriſt and his people. It is better to be ſtraightned in expreſſion, than in affection. If there be much of <hi>heart,</hi> it matters not how little of <hi>Art</hi> there be: for what ſome men moſt admire, God leaſt regards, as that uſefull man ſpeakes <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Venning.</hi>
               </note> after his manner; It is good to be zealouſly affected alwayes in a good thing. Zeale without knowledge wants eyes; knowledge without zeale wants feete. If it makes way at all, it is after a ſnayles pace, coldly, heavily, dully. We doubt not to anſwer that man, that ſhould ſay to us as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> to <hi>Luther, You are hot like fire;</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> anſwered <hi>Eraſmus, You are cold like froſt</hi> in Gods matters. We are perſwaded Zeale is more wanting all along than is knowledge, though there may be a want alſo; and we well know what is the cauſe of that want of zeale we meane; <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>For they that warmed their hearts at the Fire of Gods love, thinke zeale it ſelfe to be Coldneſſe, and Fruit fullneſſe to be barrenneſſe,</hi>
               </q> as ſaid holy <hi>Sibbes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. If our <hi>prudence</hi> be queſtioned here, no great matter neither, If having leſſe of the Serpent, we have more of the Dove. I deſire ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> in his Epiſtle to his freind <hi>Gerbelius,</hi> to approve my ſelfe a faithfull ſervant of Chriſt and His Church, if I cannot be a <hi>prudent</hi> one.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:15"/>
            <p>Drawing up to a cloſe, we would only adde this, our only deſire in reference to what we have ſpoken of our ſelves, here or hereafter ſhall ſpeak (for ſo we are compelled) That it may be underſtood ſpoken not ſo much to ſhew what our <hi>Attainments</hi> are in the things of our Lord, as what in deſire and endeavour, we would attaine unto. But ſpecially, That it may be underſtood of them all over the Nation, who walk with a right foote in a Goſpel way.</p>
            <p>We will cloſe our Letter unto you, and with you all, if it may be, in <hi>Pauls</hi> words, we thinke, we can ſpeake them heartily. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>God is our record, how heartily we long after you all in the bowells of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </q> And <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 8, 9, 10, 11. Strive we with God in prayer for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and we ſhall not ſtrive in anger one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> this we pray, That your Love may abound yet more and more in knowledge, and in all judgement. That ye may approve things that are excellent; that ye may be ſincere, and without offence, till the day of Chriſt, Being filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe, which are by Jeſus Chriſt, unto the glory and praiſe of God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:15"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving named thee</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>we account thee one of the very beſt or very worſt in all the world; like thoſe figgs</hi> (Jer. 24. 3.) If good, very good; If bad, very bad; <hi>or like the</hi> Vine (Ezek. 15) <hi>If fruitfull, the very beſt; If barren, the very worſt; worſe than thornes and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, theſe will ſerve to ſtop a gap better than Roſes or Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary; Theſe ſerve for ſome uſe, ſo not a barren Vine, nor a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See D. G. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of growth. p. 19.</note> 
               <hi>barren Chriſtian; he doth but cumber the ground, he ſhall</hi> be taken away and caſt into the fire, <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> Joh. 15. 2. 6. 26. <hi>His being a branch in Chriſt, (which we muſt obſerve in paſſage) ſhall not help him at all, but rather further increaſe, and haſten his condemnation, being to be underſtood in reſpect not of</hi> internall implantation, <hi>but</hi> externall profeſſion; <hi>he hath the</hi> viſibility <hi>of a branch, not the</hi> reallity; <hi>not by any</hi> internall communion, <hi>but</hi> outward profeſſion, <hi>as a branch that hath no coalition with the tree, nor receiveth any juice or nouriſhment from it; ſo neither hath this perſon any inward participation of efficacy from Christ;</hi> he is in Him <hi>by outward baptiſme only, but not baptized into Chriſt by the inward work of the</hi> Word and Spirit <hi>(in thoſe that are growne up to yeares, for the Spirit workes alone in Infants as wonderfully, as is the knitting and growing of the bones in the womb of her that is with Childe) whereof he gives cleare evidence, not having</hi> put-on Chriſt, <hi>nor walking</hi> in Him, <hi>he is not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Him; he hath no communion with Him, no partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb facs="tcp:119016:16"/> from Him of life and holineſſe, therefore he muſt be</hi> taken <hi>away, and</hi> caſt into the fire. <hi>It ſhall be dealt unto him as unto the barren Vine, which being not for</hi> fruit, <hi>muſt be for</hi> fewell, <hi>Ezek. 15. 4. Once more and more plainly, Thou art as the</hi> Jew <hi>was, If indeed a</hi> Jew, <hi>and</hi> inwardly, <hi>he was one of the excellent of the earth. But if one</hi> outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>and in name onely, he was the baſeſt of all men. A very provocation to God, and a very abomination; for,</hi> ſaying he was a Jew, he blaſphemed, <hi>Rev. 2. 9. and a very loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome perſon he is among the</hi> living in Jeruſalem, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans indeed, being dead while he liveth, <hi>and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſuch, how dead will he be when he dyeth,</hi> being twice dead; <hi>now dead as to that death we are all involved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by nature; and dead to all the means of quickening,</hi> and plucked-up by the roots; <hi>in no capacity now by the ſent of water to revive and quicken againe, which ſoareſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can befall none but the</hi> Jewes <hi>then and</hi> Chriſtians <hi>now. This being a point of ſo great and general concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, In our tendereſt love unto Thee, we take leave to be more large that we may be more plaine about it. And truly our Drift is to remove ſome grand-miſtakes, relating to this</hi> Name <hi>and</hi> Thing <hi>we commonly call</hi> Chriſtian <hi>or</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; <hi>There are ſome errours about it, which we have heard or reade ſome-where, may be called</hi> Beelzebub-<hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, being as pernicious, we thinke, and damnable, as any</hi> hereſie <hi>can be: ſo as, if we are taken with them, we are fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully miſtaken, and undone for ever; We would narrow theſe things what poſſibly we can. This is the firſt</hi> grand-er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the</hi> Civil honeſt man, <hi>he is the</hi> Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>who attends only</hi> the Negative Commandments, Thou ſhalt not kill. <hi>He hath obeyed God therein, for he hath layd violent hands upon no man. Nor hath he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> bodily adultery <hi>with Maide or Wife; he ſtands cleare</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:16"/> 
               <hi>to God as to that matter alſo; nor hath he violently taken away any mans goods, a ſin to be</hi> puniſhed by the Judges, <hi>he is cleare at that point too; He minds</hi> Affirmative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts <hi>as wel as the Negative, though he underſtandeth them not at all, in their comprehenſive ſenſe or latitude. This is the Chriſtian man though, And his negative godlineſſe, he is neither drunkard, nor murtherer, whore-maſter, nor theife, ſhall intitle him to Church-communions here, and to fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Saints hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A grand a Beelzebub errour! That any man living under the means of ſalvation, inſtructed out of Gods word dayly, ſhould get paſſe for a Christian, and knowes nothing as he ought to know touching the</hi> depth <hi>and</hi> breadth <hi>of the</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of original ſin, <hi>nor</hi> of the myſtery of the dutyes comprehended in Gods law, <hi>and then nothing at all of the</hi> myſtery of Grace <hi>by Jeſus Chriſt. A Chriſtian, though but in his owne conceite; for he is indeed, living in a land</hi> of viſions, <hi>much worſe than is the worſt heathen, though you ſuppoſe him a</hi> Sodomite, <hi>or a worſhipper of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is another miſtake much the ſame with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>That there is a middle perſon or a middle ſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and evil, godly (in Chriſt Jeſus) and ungodly</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>(out of Chriſt.) The truth is, there is nothing between good and evil, light and darkneſſe, no medium of participation between theſe extreames.</hi> Solomon, <hi>Eccleſ. 9. 2. rankes all in two orders, ſo doth a greater than</hi> Solomon, <hi>our Lord and Master,</hi> Math. 5. 45. <hi>This is the</hi> dichotomie, <hi>the diviſion that runnes through the whole world,</hi> righteous <hi>or</hi> wicked, good <hi>or</hi> bad, cleane <hi>or</hi> uncleane; <hi>good and evil in a remiſſe degree may be mingled in the ſame perſon, but no mans perſon is in a middle ſtate between good and evil. And ſuppoſe him, as here we muſt, to be a Christian, he is very good or very bad, the beſt in all the world, or the very worſt; there is not an</hi> allmoſt <hi>a Chriſtian in all the world,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:17"/> 
               <hi>he is altogether or not at all a Chriſtian, &amp; then worſe than can be the worſt heathen in all the world. And it is a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conceite to thinke the contrary, and mindes us how Mr</hi> Smith, <hi>an able Preacher in his time, argued the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of that Conceite (take it in paſſage) The woman in travel was</hi> almoſt <hi>delivered, not</hi> altogether, <hi>which coſt the life of the Mother and the Infant both. It is ſo in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, in a Christian land we meane, where</hi> Chriſt is preached, <hi>to be almost a Chriſtian, that is, to be altogether an heathen and worſe, though the worst among the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It matters not then, where thou, or we ranke our ſelves; and as little where our Miniſters rank us, nor what account we have of our ſelves, nor how our Miniſters reckons of us, or deales forth unto us. What are we in Scripture account, among whom doth the word of God ranke us? we have read ſome-where,</hi> That Scripture-Chriſtianity <hi>is as farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that, which paſſeth for Chriſtianity in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of moſt men, as the</hi> Sun <hi>is from a</hi> Glow-worme, <hi>which is but a ſlimey earth-worme, and caſteth ſome luſter in a darke night. Therefore for the remooving of this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, let us heare what the holy Scripture ſaith, Thou mayst be more chained-in than is another from running-ut into the ſame exceſſe of riot; but if this be all, this is nothing at all to render thee a Chriſtian. This is the Diviſion; Thou art changed in thy nature, and in thy actions, or not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; renued in the ſpirit of thy minde, or not renued; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the out ward-man in practiſe and converſation, and in the inward man in thy minde, yea in the</hi> ſpirit <hi>of thy minde, if not in both, then in neyther of both; Thou art of the</hi> firſt Adam, <hi>in whom all dye; or taken out of him by the glorious worke of the Spirit of Grace with His word, and brought-up to the</hi> ſecond Adam, <hi>in whom all are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; thou art dead or alive, dead in treſpaſſes in ſinnes, or</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:17"/> 
               <hi>being quiokened by the Word and Spirit, thou art alive to God. In a word, for we would faine remoove this miſtake; Thou art</hi> light, <hi>or thou art</hi> darkneſſe; <hi>and doe not dreame, as thou regardeſt thy pretious ſoule; for it is but a dreame that there is a middle thing betwixt theſe extreames, thou art marvelouſly</hi> light, <hi>or marvelouſly</hi> darke, <hi>light it ſelfe or darkneſſe it ſelfe. If light in the Lord</hi> (Eph. 5. 8. 1 Pet. 2. 9.) <hi>then how marvelous is that light! if darkneſſe, how</hi> great is that darkneſſe! <hi>When the light that is in thee is darkneſſe, and while the Sunne of the Goſpel ſhines round-about thee: we ſay againe, how great is that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the greater and more hideous, the more glorious the light is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And let not that which looks like light deceive thee, nor thy looking more like a Chriſtian than others may doe; thou wilt be the worſe for that, for looking like a Chriſtian, and not one indeed, thou wilt looke like an</hi> Ape <hi>in Chriſtianity, whoſe great deformity is, (And therefore we hold in great ſcorne to be likened unto an</hi> Ape) <hi>in this, becauſe he is ſo like man. Copper, we know, is never rejected but when it would paſſe for ſilver; The Devil was never ſo like himſelfe as when he ſeemed covered with</hi> Samuels Mantle, <hi>or look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like an Angel of light; as a Chriſtian in name only lookes never ſo like a Devil, as when he lookes like a Saint at the Lords Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A third miſtake, and if we miſtake not one of the greateſt magnitude, what</hi> Chriſtianity <hi>or a true</hi> Chriſtian <hi>is? He is one (the common conceite) that doth performe ſome knowne dutyes, and abſtaineth from groſſe ſins, This is well and to be commended, but if this be all, we know who condemneth it to the lower moſt hell; for what is it, in dread of that wrath that is written, ſhall be the portion of thoſe familyes who call not upon Gods name,</hi> (Jer. 10. 25.) <hi>to</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:18"/> 
               <hi>pray in thy cloſet, and with thy family, and then goe to Church, while yet thou doeſt ſpeake and doe</hi> evil things as thou canſt, <hi>Jer. 3. 5. onely for ſhame of the world thou ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineſt from groſſe ſinnes. All this is ſearce Chriſtianity in forme, it will hardly render thee a Chriſtian</hi> dealba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, <hi>whited over to uſe Mr</hi> Calvins <hi>word upon</hi> Mat. 23. 27. <hi>At the most, all this and more than this makes thee but like a dead corpes, as ſomtimes thou haſt obſerved ſtuck with ſweet flowers all over it, or like a dunghill covered with ſcarlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To caſt-out this Beelzebub-errour, pray to God for his</hi> eye-ſalve, <hi>that thou mayſt ſee and perceive, heare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; That a forme of Chriſtianity is nothing in power, it is but a</hi> forme. <hi>That a name without the thing is worſe than nothing; like a dreame, that an hungry man is eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who, when he is awakened, feeleth himſelfe hungry and ſeeth nothing. It is like a</hi> Title <hi>without</hi> reality, <hi>a miſerable comfort, to be</hi> titularly <hi>rich, and</hi> really <hi>poore. To beare-up a mans ſelfe upon fleſhly priviledges is an high preſumption, and the higher thou art built-up upon it, the more terrible thy ruine will be; for if the</hi> fleſh of Chriſt profiteth nothing, <hi>Joh. 6. 63. And if we now know</hi> not Chriſt after the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 16. leſſe muſt we know a Chriſtian after the fleſh, becauſe he bath ſome carnall or fleſhly priviledge: Well; he is not a Chriſtian then who hath no more but what we may call</hi> fleſh, <hi>ſome outward thing; but he is a Chriſtian truly and indeed,</hi> in whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5. Col. 1. 27.</note> 
               <hi>himſelfe is the hope of his glory; for Chriſt without us, all that glorious Redemption wrought by him, but a broad and without doores in the world, can profit us no more, than cloaths on anothers backe, or meate in anothers ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, or the ſpirit of holineſſe in anothers heart; A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an indeed is Chriſt in the ſoule, the</hi> Anointing of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:119016:18"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> new creature, <hi>the</hi> divine nature, <hi>the image of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rooted in the heart, and fruited in the life; he is, as the whole Church, and every part is,</hi> the habitation of <note place="margin">Eph. 2 22.</note> God by the Spirit. <hi>He is</hi> godly in Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>the power of godlineſſe is in him, and with him, his whole converſation is a meere mortification, a very hell to fleſh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Perpelua na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> violentia.</note> 
               <hi>and blood; he is ſtill offering a ſacred violence thereunto; he prayes, and in prayer, prayes earneſtly; he heares, and he heares in hearing, he heares as for his life, in deſire and indeavour that he may heare, and live. There is no duty he performes, but it putteth him to coſt; a meere outſide Chriſtian, not ſo, he will heare and pray, but all this he can doe with little or no trouble, all his care is for this, that his</hi> fleſh <hi>be put to no</hi> coſt; <hi>he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther performe an hundred thouſand Religious dutyes, than to put himſelfe to the torment of crucifying one luſt pleaſant or profitable. Once more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Chriſtian indeed ſpeakes of the Sacraments, as the holy Scripture doth,</hi> contemptibly of them, <hi>when theſe are</hi> reſted <hi>upon, and</hi> gloried <hi>in, as they are by the outſide-man, this Chriſtian in name onely. Circumciſion is</hi> nothing, <hi>and availeth nothing; Baptiſme as little, and availeth as little. The Paſſeover is nothing, and avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth nothing. Receiving at the Lords Table is as little, and availeth as little. The new creature is all, and doth all, and receiveth all, the Lord Christ and all, our</hi> Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſacrificed for us. <hi>Thus contemptibly as the ſacred Scripture doth, he ſpeaketh of the Sacraments, when as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid. But when the Inſtitution is obſerved, together with the proper uſe of them, and bleſſed intendment the Lord Chriſt had in the inſtituting of them, then as the Scripture doth, ſo doth he ſpeake gloriouſly of them. And ſo we come to the fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:19"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The fourth miſtake, as great, and deadly, as any of the former,</hi> How thou cameſt to thy Chriſtianity? <hi>or how thou waste made a Chriſtian? The common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite is, and a meere conceite it is, That to be ſprinkled on the face with water makes us Chriſtians; This was our conceite, and we are ſure tis thine, if thou art not truely a Chriſtian? Thou wast baptized, and ever ſince in thine owne account, and others,</hi> a Chriſtian. <hi>Thou art not wholly, or alltogether miſtaken herein, yet ſuch a miſtake there may he that may procure thee deſperate ſorrow at the end of thy dayes, when thou art launching forth into the wide Ocean of Eternity, where thou muſt continue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, eyther everlaſtingly bleſſed, or vnſpeakably miſerable for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Outward Baptiſme gave thee thy name</hi> Chriſtian; <hi>but there is a worke wrought within by the Spirit and the Word on Gods part, and faith on thine, that gives with the</hi> Name <hi>the</hi> thing, <hi>and the name without the thing is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and renders thee worſe than nothing, a meere va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, a thing of nothing. All holy actions come from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in firſt, and thence to the outward man: A Chriſtian, within firſt, then, ſure enough, he is one without. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to remove this grand errour, or to doe what we can, obſerve well what was hinted before, and we can but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it now. It is the voice of Chriſt in the Miniſtry of His Goſpel, heard, obeyed and beleived, that makes us true Chriſtians. All the Angells in Heaven, much leſſe all the waters in the Sea, are not able to turne one ſinner upon earth, and make him cleane, that is, make him truely Chriſtian; but the Word in the Spirits hand, having the Lords ſeale of Inſtitution upon it, that onely can doe it. Now put this to thy heart as thou canſt. Hast thou heard God ſpeaking his Word unto thee? that is, hath the Spirit.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:19"/> 
               <hi>ſpoke the Word to thy ſpirit, which the Miniſter ſpake to thy eare? (as farre as he could poſſibly carry it, to the eare, and ſo farre when time was, his hand bare the water to the face.) Hath thy heart heard the Word, has thy ſoule been liſtod up to it? And in making anſwer hereunto the Lord God chargeth thee not to hearken what thy owne heart ſayth, the moſt notorious deceiver, the verieſt jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glar in the world; no nor what the Miniſter ſayth, if he ſpeakes his owne words, which are but his dreames, and not the words of his God, being as his mouth and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ſtead. Hearken what the Lord ſayth in his Word, That thou art not made Chriſtian, if the Word in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits hand hath not made a thorow change in thee, as well of thy</hi> nature <hi>as of thy</hi> actions, <hi>This is the onely meanes, where and when God gives them, whereby we are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from darkneſſe to light; from death to life;</hi> life <hi>and</hi> mortality <hi>is brought to light to the ſoule by the Goſpels voyce, or the voyce of Chriſt in the Goſpel; which alone quickeneth the dead, awakeneth the ſleeper, bids him ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up for his light is come; Put it then to the queſtion, Haſt thou heard this voyce? Thou hast; Then thou art a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian indeed; Thou haſte not heard this voyce, Then thou art, as was ſaid, worſe than an Infidel in the remoateſt parts of the world, being but a waſhed heathen, and doeſt ſlighting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe over the meanes, whereby thou mightest underſtand thy caſe, and the way to better it: And now if thou wilt ſeale the Stone upon thy graves mouth, and make thy condition irrecoverable, (which we would be as loath Thou ſhouldeſt doe, as that thou ſhouldeſt thruſt thy ſelfe upon the mouth of a Cannon charged againſt thy breaſt with a Bullet of a tallent weight) yet if thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to undoe thy ſoule for ever, hasten (ſo Sathan, and thy fooliſh heart will adviſe thereto, and thy Miniſter will</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:20"/> 
               <hi>admit thee) together with the heards and droves of men in thy caſe unto the Lords Table, to</hi> receive Chriſt <hi>there, whom thou haſte</hi> rejected in the Goſpel; <hi>This will doe it, and nothing more certainly than this, for there thou ſhalt eate and drinke damnation to thy ſelfe, not diſcerning the Lords body. Therefore deſire of the Lord He would make thee ſerious in this matter. Hath the Word been prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thy ſoule, to make thee a</hi> childe, <hi>a</hi> ſonne <hi>or a</hi> daughter? <hi>Then thou haſte the heart of a Childe to thy heavenly Father; Thou wilt breake his Commandements as willingly and ſtudiouſly as thou wilt thy bones; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Him, with full conſent of will, when with the ſame will thou offendest the</hi> apple <hi>of thine eye; And now thou mayeſt be aſſured He hath the heart of a Father towards thee; Thou haſte the priviledge of a Childe, a warranted right to all Church Communions here; thou art inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted-in and poſſeſſed-off, being new borne, all thy ſoule can deſire, open the mouth of it never ſo wide; Onely we repeate againe, make it thy worke and thy very buiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to make this ſure to thy owne ſoule,</hi> thou art borne againe. <hi>Its meere preſumptioneſſe, as holy</hi> Bolton <hi>ſayd to his deare Children when he was dying, To thinke that God will receive our ſoules to heaven, whom He hath not renued here on earth; This being a grounded truth,</hi> for a man to be alwayes the ſame, <hi>he was from the womb, borne a childe under wrath, and in that ſtate dying,</hi> is certaine and irricoverable death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh! this undoes many, even all that are undone, are undone by it; As they never dreame of a change, which death will one day make upon them, ſo they never deſire a change, that grace in this preſent life ſhould worke on them, Therefore heare the Counſell that worthy man Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Burgeſſe <hi>gives thee; As</hi> Job <hi>ſayd of the change by</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:20"/> 
               <hi>death,</hi> He would every day waite till his change come, <hi>Job 14. 14. Doe thou ſay of this change by grace, I will every day pray, heare, reade, meditate, mourne and roare out before God, every day and all the day long, till this ſpirituall change come; And doe not accept of the Miniſters invitation to the Lords Table (though thou findeſt him very gentile and courteous this way) before this change be wrought, or in a way of working; for heare what that worthy Man ſayth;</hi> Heathens, Fornicatours, Idolaters, Adulterers, Theeves, Covetous, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, Revilers, Extortioners, became waſhed and cleanſed by the Word; <hi>but waſhed Fornicatours, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp;c. we meane, Baptized Drunkards, Theeves, Covetous, Theſe ſit under the Word and reforme nothing, but make a ſcorne of it. What may be the reaſon? Why? They live in the practiſe of knowne ſinnes, and in the neglect of knowne dutyes, under the dayly exerciſe of the Word, and yet frequent the Lords Table, which hath provoked a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Cenſure, and ſorest judgement, now wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them; whence it is as the Clay under the Sunne, ſo theſe become more obdurate under the Word, from which judgement the Lord deliver thee and us all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But beware of this as thou tendereſt thy life, (therefore we caution thee againe,) That thou dost not goe to the Lords Table in a conceite, preſumption rather, thou ſhalt receive Chriſt Jeſus the Lord there, whom thou haſte not received in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel. Remember and forget not,</hi> The rocke ſhall not be removed out of his place, <hi>as was ſpoken by</hi> Job, <hi>that is, God will not change the courſe, which He hath ſetled as firmely as the Rockes, or as the Earth, He will not alter His method, nor goe out of the way He hath preſcribed; His Word ſhall profit thee firſt, before any thing elſe ſhall or can; thou</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:21"/> muſt keepe cloſe to His way, if thou lookeſt to attaine His end.</p>
            <p>We intended more to thee, ſo dearly we love thee, as to minde thee well, there are but two <hi>Maſters</hi> that can be ſerved, and to which of theſe thou art an obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, the Apostle will tell thee. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 16, 17, 18. (2) And as there are but two rankes or ſorts of people, whereof before, ſo alſo but two <hi>wayes,</hi> the roade way of the world, the broad way; the roade way of the Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones, the way of holineſſe, where the uncleane can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe, nor any Lion can be, nor ravenous Beaſts, being a <hi>ſtraight</hi> and a <hi>narrow</hi> way, which theſe cannot indure, And thou muſt certainly know in what way thy foote walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, for ſuppoſe it the <hi>narrow</hi> way, and thou wilt finde thy fleſh pinched, if not tormented. (3) And that there are but two Manſion houſes, where thy ſoule anon, and thy body anon after, muſt dwell that long day, or night of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the <hi>narrow</hi> way tendeth to the one, the <hi>broad</hi> way to the other; If now thou wilt conferre with fleſh and blood, we know what way thou wilt chooſe, the broad way, and hell to be thy Manſion houſe for ever; for though thou mayſt have, as the wicked may have, a <hi>Velliety,</hi> a faint will for Heaven, to <hi>dye the death of the righteous,</hi> and <hi>that thy laſt end may be like his;</hi> yet, walking in that <hi>broad</hi> way, the ſtrength of thy will carryeth thee hell-ward, that horrid place of darkneſſe, Therefore give-up thy hand to God, having fixed thy eye upon His Word, and ſay, Lord plucke me into the way, and leade me in it, and ſuffer me not to decline from it.</p>
            <p>In all this we intended to be more large; And to touch lightly upon other things alſo, the ſubject matter of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe, but this well digeſted and pondered-on may ſuffice; And it will be ſufficient, though thou readeſt
<pb facs="tcp:119016:21"/> not one word of the Booke; for ſuppoſe thou art made a Diſciple indeed, a Chriſtian in truth, thou wilt ſeperate from the world, at the Lords Table, nor wilt thou <hi>eate,</hi> that is, familiarly converſe with the men of the world, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe neceſſarily (as a Phyſitian with the ſick) having thy warrant for it, thou mayſt convey good unto them, and thine owne affaires may require it. And (2) Thou canſt no more obſerve the <hi>day,</hi> the men of the world call <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> than thou canſt prophane the Lords day; for thou mayst have heard that one being asked whether he did obſerve the Lords day, keeping it holy? <hi>Yes,</hi> ſayd be, <hi>for I am a Chriſtian.</hi> And doe you obſerve <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas day,</hi> to keepe it holy? <hi>No,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for then I were no Chriſtian, unleſſe in name, and that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing indeed.</hi> A true Chriſtian <hi>flees from Idolatry,</hi> for what hath he any more to doe with Idols? <hi>And be will not put up his Petitions in anothers words, he</hi> praiſeth <hi>God for what he hath received, he</hi> prayeth <hi>to God for what he would receive; he confeſſeth the ſinnes he hath committed, all this with his owne mouth: He uſed ſet formes of Prayer, when time was, hee was a Chriſtian in name onely; but now that he is, through grace, a Chriſtion indeed, he remembers heartily, that a prayer by the Booke left him as cold as it found him, it had no more heate in it, than hath cold Iron or froſt, and had he not layd them aſide, he had proved a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an when an Ape prooves a man; he bares himſelfe-up as formerly, upon the</hi> crutches <hi>then, as others now doe, and he was as well in his owne conceite as others now are; bare</hi> formes <hi>never put the fleſh to any paine; But to feele no paine, Comes, we know, from the rottenneſſe of the fleſh as well as ſoundneſſe. A dead Chriſtian, ſuch as he, that hath but a name that he liveth, feeles no paine, hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119016:22"/> 
               <hi>all is well with him, and preſumption being a ſinne of mans-ſelfe flattering-heart, meets with no trouble; though he be deſperately wicked, that is,</hi> deadly ſick unto death, <hi>yet aske him how he doth, and he ſayes well, for he was baptized when time was, and dealt with as a Saint, he thankes his good Miniſter, ever ſince he grew up to the yeares of underſtanding. But little doth he know how hardly that</hi> diſeaſe <hi>is curable, that is ſo like to health;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ille morbus vix ſanabitur, qui ſanitatem vini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur.</note> 
               <hi>one ſayth,</hi> ſeldome or never; <hi>and he addeth,</hi> None are more deſperate than thoſe, that are leaſt deſpairing in their owne ſelves, <hi>through not of the grace of God; preſumers therefore are in the more deſperate condition, by how much they are the leſſe deſpairing. But what a ſad thing is it that men ſhould preſume they are rich and want nothing, when they are miſerably poore and want all things, we will pitty thoſe deluded mad men, who are perſwaded, they are ſuch great perſons, and have ſuch large eſtates, when in the meane time they lye miſerable and wretched bound up in chaines in a darke dungeon; ſuch a ſpirituall madneſſe is upon moſt, and this renders them more mad, if more can be; they were baptized, and upon that Infant priviledge, have free admiſſion to the Lords Table, without making the leaſt profeſſion of faith and repentance, wherein it comes to paſſe, that as they live like mad men, ſo they are like to ciye, being ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded ſtill upon principles of Infant Baptiſme, That, they are</hi> Diſciples <hi>and</hi> Saints, <hi>while they are</hi> Drunkards <hi>and</hi> Devills; <hi>they are</hi> ſheepe <hi>and</hi> lambs, <hi>when they are</hi> dogges <hi>and</hi> ſwine; <hi>And call themſelves</hi> grapes <hi>and</hi> figges, <hi>when they are</hi> thornes <hi>and</hi> thiſtles, <hi>to uſe, and ſo to end with that Learned Mr</hi> Burgeſſe <hi>his words:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119016:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Love, that ſpares no coſt, nor feeleth any burthen, hath drawne us-out thus farre, conſider what hath been ſayd, meditate upon it, be wholly in it, and ſo doing, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever fareth ill, thou ſhalt fare well.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
